<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Remarks upon E. Settle's Narrative</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B28883</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99890433</idno>
  <idno type="VID">201978</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240918415</idno>
  
            <idno type="OCLC"> 11885554</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R943</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide T.88*.[63]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3866</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99890433</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99890433e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B28883)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 201978)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; C30:1[62])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Remarks upon E. Settle's Narrative</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 17, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by A. Banks for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Settle, Elkanah, 1648-1724. --  Narrative --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Popish Plot, 1678 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:201978:1"/>
            <p>REMARKS UPON <hi>E. Settle's</hi> NARRATIVE</p>
            <q>
               <l>Nil Aliud loqueris quam <hi>Thesea, Perithoumque</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Teque putas <hi>Pyladi, Calliodore,</hi> Parem.</l>
               <l>Dispeream, si tu <hi>Py adi</hi> prestare matellam</l>
               <l>Dignus es, aut Porcos pascere <hi>Perithoi</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed and are to be sold by <hi>A. Banks</hi> for the Author, 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:201978:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:201978:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>And is <hi>E. Settle</hi> turn'd Recanter! nay then, there may be some hopes of the conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of the Devil and all his Angels. But his own fellow Poets will not believe it; they, in their <hi>Prologues,</hi> say he has only <hi>turn'd Cat in Pan.</hi> And thus again all our hopes touching the <hi>Devil</hi> expire. For alas, he is no more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted then <hi>Satan</hi> himself, &amp; this his preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Recantation</hi> and <hi>Narrative,</hi> proves only an <hi>Expedient</hi> to satisfie the importunate cries of his necessity. What signifies the submissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of such a sordid <hi>Animall</hi> to an offended Prince, that shall prostrate himself at the Feet of any Common <hi>Harlot,</hi> that will but be at the <hi>Expence</hi> of a <hi>Bully,</hi> to correct his misdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors. Forgiveness is too high for such <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi>-cowring. Such a one does not repent, but basely fawne under the terrours of what he deserves. Like the <hi>Devil,</hi> he only believes he has done a miss, <hi>&amp;</hi> trembles. Therefore he is not forgiv'n, but only spurn'd, contemn'd &amp; let live. And now shall such a slave, fetter'd in the chains of his still clamouring transgressions, be thought a Credible Umpire to determin the cause of <hi>Popish Treason</hi> and <hi>Murder?</hi> shall he be the proper <hi>Judge</hi> of National Wisdom and Justice? shall his tainted breath be thought suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to blast a <hi>Popish-Plot,</hi> upon all the stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctest scrutinies <hi>&amp;</hi> enquiries of moderation <hi>&amp;</hi> prudence so voted to by the highest Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie of the Realm? Consider, Readers with your selves, and so farewell.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:201978:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:201978:3"/>
            <head>REMARKES UPON <hi>E. Settle's</hi> NARRATIVE</head>
            <p>AND now the <hi>Whiggs</hi> may thank themselves. They had once the <hi>Great Settle</hi> on their sides. There were but Nine Muses, and four &amp; a half were <hi>Whiggs</hi>—But now for want of a little Contribution-money to defend him from Taylors Bills, and Landlady's scores, they have lost this mighty Champion of <hi>Theirs.</hi> 'Tis an ill thing to provoke the slaves of Patrons, that have no where to feed but at other mens Tables; that have no bread to put in their heads but what their Patron affords 'em: for these Tenants at Will under other men's Roofs must sneake and cringe, and if a Patron will have 'em, must damn their souls, to save their Bodies. The <hi>Tories</hi> therefore would not loose the Opportunitie, but finding such a <hi>Belisarius</hi> as <hi>Elkanah,</hi> deserted, first by his <hi>Patron Roffee,</hi> that kept the <hi>King</hi>'s <hi>Armes</hi> against the <hi>Dukes Theatre,</hi> and forsaken by his <hi>Aldersgate street</hi> Patron, presently caught him up, fed him, and set him to work. 'Twas all one to <hi>Elkanah,</hi> what car'd He? He followd the Dictates of his Necessitie, and, <hi>Ingenij Largitor venter.</hi> The <hi>Whiggs</hi> therefore were nothing at all beholding to him; for it was not any good opinion of their cause, or upon any true Ground or principle of vertue and reason that he did them service. But being a needy Pedler of words, sold 'em to the best Chapman, as the Italian <hi>Bravos</hi> prostitute their Pistolls and still etto's to all the leud Designs of Mischeif. Nay he is so vain and ostentatious to make the world beleive, that his Satyrs had effectual Gall, and that the Blemishes of his Pen would most severely stick where they lighted. And who d'yee think must be the first that was to feel the signall Effects of his wrath and disgust? No less a Personage then his <hi>Rooyal Highness.</hi> This he thought was <hi>Par Congressus,</hi> and would render his fame Immortall. And what was all this for? Because the Duke was not pleasd to gratifie his humour about an Idle Play. A crime assuredly of a most high nature, scarce within the bounds of pardon, for an inconsiderable <hi>Play—Wright</hi> to bend the force of his Poeticall Licence in the defence of a cause by him self
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:201978:4"/>not approv'd, and consequently to put an Imposture upon the Nation to endeavour to dethrone the Kingdomes Heir, on purpose to satisfie his Rancour and Revenge against the Duke. And all this not out of his zeale for the public Welfare, but out of Malice forethought against the second person of the Realm, contrary to his conscience, his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and opinion.</p>
            <p>It is a small satisfaction for so high an offence, to come with a glozing panegyric and think to cover former injuries with the tawdry vaile of a peice of flattery. For if ascribing praise be a doing Honour, the person that Honours must be truly qualified to give it. But the world will hardly be brought to beleive, that it can be any more Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our for a person of Sublime worth and dignity to be applauded by a prostituted pen, then for a Lady of high birth and untainted vertue to be extoll'd by a common strumpet. Rather will they beleive that such a <hi>Magnifyer</hi> would not stick to take the same hire again to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the same transgression, were he in the same wide world under the same Temptation. More then this; had he determind to have shew'd the realitie of his penitence by the cleverness of his proceedings, it had been more proper for Mr. <hi>Settle</hi> to have storm'd his own book, and to have batter'd it with all the force of his Tragic-fury, thn to fall with such a hungry Appetite upon the Plot, which receives no farther Detriment from this assault of his, but only that it will be thought to have been so Charitable as to have fed him all this while of his last Retirement. And had he not, in his own conceit quite annihilated the Plot, the Lord knows how long he might have eat and drank upon the Plot. But it seems he was weary of dyeting too long upon one dish. All his Friends, even to the Draggle-tayl'd Female are sorry for him, and wish him a good Concoction; yet they vehemently fear 'twill cost him a most terrible surfet. <hi>Plots</hi> and <hi>Poultrey-Counters</hi> are wicked hard of Disgestion.</p>
            <p>Our Narrative-Monger might have learnt discretion from the <hi>Obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vator:</hi> He was wise and politick, and always warie how he deny'd the Plot it self; and therefore liu'd upon it for several years, only by Skirmishing with the Witnesses. He, like a wastful prodigal, Ruins and consumes all at once, before he knows where to have more; for 'tis to be fear'd he wants learning to enlarge upon the <hi>Critic Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story of the Old-Testament.</hi> But Mr. <hi>Settle</hi> will never leave his <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sh-Tricks.</hi> Had he repeated his <hi>Narrative,</hi> as he was wont to do his Tragic Scenes, by bits and Scraps to the Scullers in <hi>Roffee's</hi> Ale-Box<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, they would have given him better advice then he has taken.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Mr. Settle</hi> was misled by many, and <hi>those the greatest men in England,</hi> whom he would involve in the same Crime. So people in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the Plague, out of a particular Malice inherent to that disease, labour to bring others under the same Contagion. To which purpose they find him endeavouring to set up for a new
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:201978:4"/>Evidence, though, according to his usual folly, a day after the Fair, and accusing the dead <hi>for bidding him speak more favourably of Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> A thing altogether as improbable as any thing he has objected against <hi>Oates</hi> and <hi>Bedlow,</hi> that a person of that known Experience and reserv'd Wisdom, were there nothing else, should make such an open Declaration of his mind to such a one as Mr. <hi>Settle.</hi> For deep and wary Politicians will not so easily trust a <hi>Hireling.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Macnamarr</hi> and <hi>Zeale</hi> for that. He whom the <hi>Towring Poet</hi> in his Epistle to the <hi>Female-Prelate</hi> calls <hi>Englands fastest Friend,</hi> of whose great services for <hi>England, the most ignorant of the Orcades were full;</hi> whose Counsils to the King <hi>were unshook</hi> by frowns, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brib'd by honors; he who had <hi>so Strenuouslly and so justly labour'd to defeat a dangerous Faction, no less threatning then a growing Phaeton,</hi> this flattering Sycophant, having spent and forgot his Dedication mony, without any respect to Gratitude or his own Reputation safely now besmears that once ador'd Honor, pronounces all this to be mere Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic Flames, and Damn'd Flattery, and accuses his deceased▪ Patron of a most improbable piece of Treason. And therefore what man of sense or reason will so far prejudice himself, as to believe a <hi>Scrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of his Profession</hi> (for so he Stiles himself) that runs a trust upon the hopes of a Dedication, and studies Encomiums with the same Mercenary Soul, as Fidlers play at Bridegrooms Windows? 'Tis either we thank your Lordship, or a pox take him, as the sum reveals it self and defrays old debts. I say what man of sence or reason can believe such a Miscreant Writer for all his Canting and recanting, though he cant and recant till Dooms-day?</p>
            <p>However, the Tide being turn'd and he having tasted other Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, the Narrative-Merchant complains, that this great man, and many others of the same Quality misguided him. But therein he tells the World a most gross untruth. For if his own words are printed right, while he wrote for them they guided him very right. For then in his <hi>Dedication to the Tories,</hi> Pocket—Inspir'd no doubt, as now, he tells the world, <hi>That their Absolons and Achitophels and the</hi> rest of their <hi>Grinning Satyrs against the</hi> Whiggs <hi>had this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardonable fault, that the Lash was more against a</hi> David <hi>then an</hi> Achi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophel, <hi>while their Ranning down of the Plot, at so extravagant a Rate, savour'd of very little less then Ridiculing of Majesty and turning all those several Royal Speeches in Parliament on that Subject only into the double-tongu'd Oracles that sounded one thing and meant another,</hi> He calls it farther the <hi>Branding the publick Just<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce of the Nation, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronting even the Throne it self.</hi> Nay he goes yet one step far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and says, <hi>That the Tories who</hi> will <hi>believe no Popish Plot, may as justly come under the Denomination of Fools, as they that</hi> David <hi>tells us, said in their hearts there was no God.</hi> This was one who says, <hi>he was no Hypocrite, for he wrote what he thought: no Clod-pated Fidler that sung against his Conscience.</hi> So then at that time, while he acted ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:201978:5"/>to the Principles of Integritie and Censcience, those great men of <hi>England</hi> certainly could be none of his misguiders. They could never be said to be his misguiders, who encourag'd him, as much as in him lay, to repress the insolence of those that sought to Ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cule Majesty and brand the publick Justice of the Nation. Now then what must he be, but a contemptible Renegado from his inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie, and a flashy Revolter from his Conscience, while he falls into those very Crimes that before he so justly tax'd in others? A young <hi>Balaam,</hi> whom the Popish <hi>Baal Peor's</hi> have hir'd to curse a Plot against his Prince and Country. Wonder not then that this new Proselyte of Satan has made use of his utmost force to <hi>Ridicule Majesty</hi> and <hi>brand the justice</hi> of the Nation in Opposition to his first Sinceritie and Conscienee. For 'tis observ'd, that there are none so violent, none so Zealous Enemies, none that study more the Extirta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of Christianity then our European Renegado's among the Turks.</p>
            <p>All this while, who is this mighty Gyant? 'Tis but Mr. <hi>Settle</hi> still. Now hear his own Description of himself: <hi>A thing so nameless and inconsiderable, that he is only to be describ'd by Negatives.</hi> which are now to be alter'd according to that shape into which he has <hi>Proteus'd</hi> himself; that is to say, a person of no integritie, nor repute, no value, no belief, no credit, no Conscience. Novv whether the mature Deliberations and Examinations of his Majesties Council &amp; both houses of <hi>Parliament</hi> are to be arraign'd at once by such a worthless Animall as this, let all the sober part of the Kings Dom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inions judge.</p>
            <p>But you'll say, he is now a <hi>Recanter:</hi> a <hi>Recanter</hi> in the Devil's name. He recants that ever he did according to his Conscience, he is sorry that he did not ridicule Majesty, and brand the publick Justice of the Nation. This is such a Recantation, that wherever it passes for such begets a strange conclusion, that there is but one great Knave in the Nation, and all the rest are Fools. For as for his personal offences against the Duke, they stand cowring only under the shelter of a short flourishing submission, not half sufficient to expiate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries committed out of Malice and Revenge, and contrary to Conscience against so great a personage. For which it could be no satisfaction to decry the plot wherein he was never in the least concern'd. So that Mr. <hi>Settle</hi> is the first since <hi>Adam'</hi> that ever alter'd the course of Recantations, and repented of acting against his conscience.</p>
            <p>But if you will not give him leave to recant, you may admitt him to reform. For he sayes he is resolv'd to renounce both the <hi>Whore</hi> and the <hi>Baud.</hi> A blessed Reformation. But it is so contrary to his Genius, which is another sort of conscience of his too, that it is never to be expected. There are those charmes in <hi>Salisbury-Court</hi> and <hi>Drury-Lane,</hi> that a youngman of his robust temper can never resist. But you'll say he does not mean those sort of Whores and Bauds; no, no, he'll never make a Narrative against them, he's as great a friend to them as ever, and 'twas for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:201978:5"/>love of them he wrote this Narrative; he means the <hi>Lust of Revenge which he gratifi'd, and the Plot that rose up to lend him means and opportunity.</hi> 'Thats but a sham. As if a man so bent to gratifie his lust as he was, and a man of so much invention could not easily have sound out a way to gratifie his passion, had the Plot never bin. 'Twas not the Plot neither, but the debate in Parliment that arose from other circumstances that gave him the opportunity. But because he? could not revenge himself upon the Parliment, there fore he resolv'd to reck his spleen upon the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus 'tis plain to all the world, that his continu'd lust of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, and no good intent to the public good, has bin the occasion of all Mr. <hi>Settles</hi> malice against the Plot. So that whatever am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mositie he may have against the <hi>Baud,</hi> he has not renounc'd the <hi>Whore</hi> yet.</p>
            <p>But now enter Sathan in Mr. <hi>Settles</hi> likeness, breaking ground and raising his first batteries against the Plott, accusations upon accsations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It has furnish'd the world with an Ocean of guilded zeale and hypocrisie.</hi> Of which the cheifest president is his nown dear Self.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It has made the greatest Atheists the greatest sticklers for R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> And is that such a crime? to bring Atheists to beleive in God? But it seems tis Mr. <hi>Settles</hi> opinion. <hi>It brought the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st rigid Fanaticks to the Church of Englands communion and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> And is Mr. <hi>Settle</hi> angrie at that? yes—for, it was <hi>to capacitate them for offices of trust.</hi> And if they were thereby fitted for those Trusts, what should hinder 'em from having them <hi>It made the greatest true Protestant Citey Dons perjure themselves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That's as far fetch'd as his Mask of <hi>Orphens</hi> and <hi>Eurid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce</hi> in the Empress of <hi>Morocco.</hi> For one swallow never makes a Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. But the Poet thinks he is versifying, and therefore takes the Libertie of a Romance. Others believe he meant <hi>Citie-Dun's,</hi> instead of <hi>Citie-Don's.</hi> For the first indeed may deserve the lash of his pen; as having been frequently Thorns in his side. The Plot would have made <hi>the Metropolis Independant from the Crown, lopp'd the Prerogative and borrow'd the Militia, to fight against Black Bills,</hi> Thus you see he is still Gratifiing his renounc'd whore, <hi>Lust of Revenge;</hi> for you must know the Poet has a peculiar Antipathy against <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lls</hi> of any sort what er'e they be, ever since the persecution of his Taylors: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fides 'tis an Intrenchment upon his Profession for any other people to utter any thing that so much as smells of a Hyperbole; a Liberty which Poets allow only to themselves. Though while he himself was talking Hyperbole's of another Nature, he might have let the <hi>Brown Bills</hi> pass, without calling the <hi>Corporal.</hi> In the mean while the Poet is to understand, that men Scholastically bred when they speak of Military Affairs, may not always be so fortunate as to express themselves in proper Military Terms. Tis enough to save the Plot from the Destruction of <hi>Settl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Briarean</hi> Folly, that there were several Discourses of Military Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:201978:6"/>'tis no matter what the weapons were, nor how call'd, whither the Discoverer spoke like a Cutler or a Gunsmith, or a Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit. But such School-Cavils, Quibles, Quirks, and Quiddities you shall meet with all along in this same <hi>Plot-Menippus</hi>'s Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive; as if the solemn Determinations of the supreme Councils of the Nation were to be confuted and baffl'd by such a slicer of Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbers, a meer Romantic Whiffler in <hi>Scotus</hi> or <hi>Zabarell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It has made the whole Body of Antipopish Dissenters in their highest Enmity against Plots and Rome, desire to be incorporated with the Church of</hi> England. What strange Crimes has this Retainer to other mens Trenchers found out against the Plot? For certainly no greater Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie could befall this Nation, then a happy union of all in General that profess the Protestant Religion against their Common Enemies the Papists. Such a League none but Sons of <hi>Belial</hi> would presume to grin at. And surely the Church of <hi>England</hi> most heartily desir'd it as much as the Dissenters, and is still ready to receive them into her Embraces. Now if this were the designe of the Plot, why did not the Plot bring it to pass? Nothing but ill luck: For the Papists smel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Plots intention, presently set all their deep-mouth'd Hounds upon her, that in a short time hunted her to a <hi>Fault:</hi> and now here's <hi>Jowler Narrative</hi> has started her again, and is resolv'd alone to run her quite down. Now I would fain know whither Mr. <hi>Settle</hi> has not done like himself to shew a dislike of the Union of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? And next whither such a <hi>Son of Division</hi> deserves to be patron'd in a Hogstie. <hi>Then the Plot writ the Association.</hi> If he mean the pretended Association. 'twas a Bastard, and so more-like to be got by himself. If he mean the Association propounded in Parliament, he ungratiously bespatters that high Assemblie of the Nation, which was so far from proceeding in what vvas propos'd vvithout his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties good liking, that they petition'd him for his assent. But vvhat signifies all this from a <hi>Bartholmew-Fair Booth-man?</hi> a <hi>Strowller</hi> about the Country vvith <hi>Farces,</hi> that betray'd his Friend <hi>Bose,</hi> vvho vvas vvont to pavvn his plate to supply his empty pocket, to the Pillory and Banishment. All vvhich the poor man patiently suffer'd, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then reveal him the Author of that damnable Lampoon, call'd a <hi>Game at Cards,</hi> presented inconsiderately to Mr. <hi>Duboys.</hi> And vve may vvith as great probability believe that the hard Fate of his Friend frighted him into this conversion, and being of a Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pooning Nature, put him upon this Lampoon against the Plot. Which is no nine days vvonder to them vvho have but cast an Eye upon his Venemous Invectives against his <hi>Royal Highness.</hi> From the severest punishment of vvhich there's nothing certainly protects him but the baseness of his Condition, vvhile men of Repute and Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, the more unhappy in their Errors, suffer for less then the Hundredth part of what this Prostitute Scribler has done.</p>
            <p>But the world does not perceive the Policie of this lofty Rimer; for could he but turn the Plot into a Fable, he would soon turn the Fable into a Farce. That, he thinks, would be a <hi>Rarie-Show</hi> indeed, to carry like <hi>Scarroons</hi> Comedians, from County to County among the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:201978:6"/>'Tis ten to one but he has begun to build Sconces already upon the Credit of the Project: And more then this, 'tis said that the <hi>Jack-Puddings</hi> begin to Petition him already for places. But as <hi>Lust of Revenge</hi> against Princes, and Treason to Friendship seldom goe unpunish'd, let him have a care this Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poon upon the Plot be not the last Act of his Play. For he is to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, that this Lampoon upon the Plot, which never any yet but profest Papists and Ribalds durst attempt, is a Lampoon upon Majesty, a Lampoon upon the Lords and Commons of <hi>England,</hi> a Lampoon upon the honour of the Judges, the learning and wisdom of the Kings Council, and the Integrity of the Juries. Worse then Varlet, he has endeavour'd to besmeare the Throne with innocent Blood; to new die the Graceful-Robes of Peerage with the Crimson Stains of Cruelty and Oppression; to dishonour the Commons of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> with the Character of Barbarous and Blood-thirsty; to involv the Judges, the Council, the Juries promiscously in the horrid crimes of Corruption and Perjurie: and all this, to offer up the Guiltless, the Beloved of God, to the <hi>Moloch</hi> of a Romantic-Plot. What no true Christian, no Man of Common Morality would have been brib'd to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake for the Guerdon of an Empire, this audacious <hi>Butter-flie</hi> of a <hi>Rimer</hi> has ventur'd at, for the small gains of a Dedication, and a little paltry Coppy-mony, to satisfie the hunger of his Debauchery. A Recantation, if it may be call'd so, and not rather a more fatal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laps into manifoldly worse transgressions then he recanted, purchas'd at a dear Rate. Yet greedily bought up by many, of whom Piety it self has this Charitable perswasion, that er'e this they have better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider'd the unhappy Consequences of their belief, and will therefore Sacrifice the Pernicious Sheets to the Flames which they deserve.</p>
            <p>Some men perhaps may not so well know, but all are to understand that this is not the first Recantation that Mr. <hi>Settle</hi> has made. It as natural as mud to an <hi>Eele,</hi> for Mr. <hi>Settle</hi> to make Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantations, somtimes out of fear, somtimes out of necessity. And it is hard to say which has the most Predominant Influence o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver him. He has twice given it under his hand that his Mother was a <hi>Whore.</hi> Once to Mr. <hi>O.</hi> as not finding himself any way pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd to die, &amp; as unwilling to forsake the Devil &amp; his beloved works.</p>
            <p>Another time there was a Certain Gentlewoman that shall be nameless, who became so far inveigl'd with his Poetry that by her he encreas'd the world with the Issue of two years. Afterwards, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of love or hatred, that he might perfect the work of undoing her, is uncertain, he would have marry'd this Gentlewoman; but she ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving doubtless had the woful Experience of his Poverty, and well understanding that four naked legs in a bed are not sufficient to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a Family, rejected his Suite. Which so inflam'd his <hi>Lust of Revenge,</hi> that he came and brake her Windows, resolving to set a Bawdy-house Mark upon her Lodging. Presently the Gentlewoman complain'd of his ill usage to a Friend: and as the complaints of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men soon find a compassionate Champion, her complaints were not fruitless. For the Gentleman taking his Opportunity, soon call'd
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:201978:7"/>the Valiant Window-breaker to an account, and gave him so severe a Cane-Correction, that Mr. <hi>Settle,</hi> who was always indulgent to his Bones, and kind and merciful to his own flesh, not enduring that sort of Discipline, fell immediately into his never failing way of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantation,</hi> and among the r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>st of the Conditions propos'd to him, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, patiently, &amp; willingly condescended to acknowledg himself the <hi>Son of a Whore.</hi> And this is the second known time that Mr. <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ttle</hi> has Valorously avoided the Just Indignation of his Enemies by defam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Womb that bore him, and acknowledging himself the spuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Brat of Adultery.</p>
            <p>Yet this is that Contemptible He, who pretends to convince his Soveraigne of Errours and Faylours in his Justice, and to put all the Lords and Commons of <hi>England</hi> upon writing <hi>Penitential-Psalms</hi> for an Inhuman Prosecution of the Innocent. And therefore,
<q>
                  <l>Quis quis Stolaeve purpurave contemptor,</l>
                  <l>Quos colere debet, laesit impio versu,</l>
                  <l>Erret per urbem, Pontis exul &amp; clivi,</l>
                  <l>Interque Raucos ultimus Rogatores</l>
                  <l>Oret caninas panis Improbi buccas.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Nevertheless, after all these crimes, far worse then those, for which he so severely sends his <hi>Lybian</hi> Empress to the other world, he vainly flatters himself in strange advantages that shall acctew from his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying thus both his Soul and his Conscience and doing injury to Heaven. For he that endeavours to insinuate such bloody Aspersions u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on Gods anointed, and those high dignities next to him, injures Heaven it self. Nor is it the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ulation of his Majesties <hi>Halcyon Raign,</hi> disturb'd by a Plot will serve his turn, while he labours to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguish the Prosecution of those that disturb it▪ I say after all this, oppress'd with the thoughts of his future happiness, he falls into an <hi>Endymions Dream,</hi> and sancies to himself <hi>that he has now shaken hands with his troublesom Compan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on Whigg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> by which perhaps he was too strictly confin'd at least to publick sobriety and moderation (for otherwise <hi>Whiggism,</hi> not Phylacteriz'd about with Libells and Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poons, walks about as freely and as unmolested, as the most Loyal. He that drowns himself in Healths to the King) and therefore he shall be at Liberty <hi>to look Sence and Quality in the Face;</hi> which he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to have done before, when he was seduc'd by great Persons. But his meaning is, that now he hopes by his Conversion, as he terms it, to be in a capacity to return to his former vain and luxurious life among the young Extravagants of the Town, where he shall have nothing to fear, unless the watchful Eyes of Bayliffs and Serjeants cause him to pull in his Horns, and creep back into his Shell. Far be it otherwise from all persons of Repute and Quality to admit him their presence contaminated with <hi>Ridiculing Majesty, and branding the Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tice of the Nation.</hi> Rather let him retire among the Turks, where if they want it, he may defend their <hi>Alcoran,</hi> or among the Jews where he may make a Studious Comment upon their Fabulous <hi>Talmud,.</hi> So Employ'd he may perhaps linger out for some time a life borrow'd from Justice, unless his despair give him up to a more early Fate.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:201978:7"/>
            <head>Here the <hi>Scene</hi> Changing, Enter <hi>Narrative,</hi> Solus, with a flourish.</head>
            <p>And here you are first to observe the scope of the Libeller's idle Discourse, which is to manifest, <hi>What an unthinking Pack of</hi> Jehu<hi>'s the</hi> Papists <hi>were, through the whole</hi> Plot, <hi>and what Lunacy and Infatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation drove 'em.</hi> Not considering what an Unthinking, Lunatick, Infatuated Fool he was at the same time: For the Lunacy and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>satuation of the <hi>Papists,</hi> in their proceedings against Hereticks, is so well known to all the World, that he might have spar'd his Labor.</p>
            <p>In the next place you are to take notice, that the weapons that he has chosen to make use of to play his Prize withal, are Quibble, Evasion, Contradiction: Weapons which he has stoll'n from the long since baffl'd <hi>Vindication of Roman Catholicks, Stafford's Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moirs, The Morocco Preist,</hi> and such like inconsiderabe Champions of <hi>Popery;</hi> and has now only new ground and whetted, lest they should be known again by their rusty Compexion. For who ever has read the lame objections which those Pampleteers have made against the Verity of the late dismal <hi>Popish Contrivance,</hi> shall find this Insolent <hi>Plot-Bravo</hi> to have only been their Ape, and to have mustred up their repeated Fallacies and Evasions to support his Insigificant, Ras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally Recantation.</p>
            <p>And now that he may be thought to begin well, his first underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king is to assassinate the Belief of the Intended assassination of his Majestie.</p>
            <p>To which purpose, after he has been prying and peering up and down for <hi>Absurdities, Contradictions,</hi> and <hi>Impossibilities,</hi> to obliterate the Consult in <hi>April,</hi> which he calls the <hi>Hinge of the whole Plot:</hi> He is extremely also astonish'd, that in <hi>Pickering</hi>'s Tryal, the <hi>Consult</hi> should consist of Fifty persons, which at <hi>Langhorn</hi>'s Tryal were <hi>dwin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dl'd</hi> into <hi>Eighteen</hi> or <hi>Twenty:</hi> But the greater wonder is, That an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>considerable namless Fellow, by his own Confession, and which by the Attestation of others, never valu'd his own Oaths, Vows or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testations, should be so nice a Critick upon other mens, and yet speak so little to the purpose. For the <hi>Consult,</hi> as all Councils, Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods and Parliaments are said to consist of their full Number, tho' tis Ten to One, whether they may be all present at one time. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides, there might have been Fifty at First, and but Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty when <hi>Langhorn</hi> was there. But saies Monsieur <hi>Narrative,</hi> The reason why the Fifty <hi>dwindl'd</hi> into so small a number was, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause <hi>'twas proved, there was never a Room in the Tavern would hold a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove a dozen;</hi> which is notoriously false: For the woman that came to Swear against her own House, became the laughter and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the Court, and the Judges told <hi>Langhorn,</hi> that she had been very unfortunate in her evidence, to be so peremptory in what the standers by knew to be so untrue. Now what becomes of this Puny <hi>Argus</hi>'s Pun of <hi>Fifty</hi> and <hi>Twenty</hi> being <hi>alike</hi> in the <hi>Sacred deliverers Arithmetick.</hi> The <hi>Verum necessarium</hi> was, that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:201978:8"/>there should be a <hi>Consult.</hi> 'Twas not <hi>Verum necessarium,</hi> whether there were fifty or twenty, so there were enough to make a <hi>Consult.</hi> But this same <hi>Evidence-splitter</hi> has nothing to say to matter of fact; he only Trades in <hi>Contradictions, Absurdities</hi> &amp; <hi>Impossibilities,</hi> Sad ware, God knows, to lay at the Top of the Basket, if he hath any better; and we would willingly allow him as much Wit as a Costermonger. For to Swear there were Fifty at <hi>Pickering</hi>'s Tryal and Twenty at <hi>Langhorn</hi>'s, was no contradiction: For in <hi>Contradictions Alterum negat ubi{que}</hi> but the Swearing of Fifty is no denyal of the Twenty, nor the Swearing of Twenty any denyal of Fifty. Mr. <hi>Slipstring</hi> with all his perspicacious peering, does not find any Oath positive, that there was but just Fifty at <hi>Pickering</hi>'s Tryal and no more, or but just Twenty and no more at <hi>Langhorn</hi>'s, so that the <hi>Ʋbi{que} negans</hi> being wanting in the same subject, the Contradiction va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishes.</p>
            <p>Looking a little further, we spie a Miracle, that <hi>Whitebread</hi> in <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary, should read an account of a crime, at St</hi> Omers, <hi>not comitted till</hi> March <hi>following:</hi> That was somewhat strange indeed, but being more strange then True, the Miracle ceases. For the demonstration of <hi>Januaries Packet,</hi> relating to the Errour committed, had no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the time of the Penance. <hi>Whitebread</hi> might give an account of the Error committed in <hi>January</hi> and <hi>Pickering</hi> not be punish'd till <hi>March,</hi> without a Miracle.</p>
            <p>But he desires the <hi>Reader not to be puzzl'd to imagine how Picker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing could present a Gun, between a Pistol and a Carbine, in a place there was not so much as a bush or a bryar to shroud a Pignee, and not be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended or seen by any of the Kings attendance.</hi> The Devils's in this fellow for putting shams upon the World. In the first place the Oath does not affirm that <hi>Pickering presented the Gun,</hi> but that finding the defect of the Flint, he deferr'd the Action till another time. Then he forgets that there was a very thick Grove at the end of the <hi>Pallmall,</hi> where His Majesty might have made his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate approaches, as well as to any other part of the Park. In the next place, fellows prepar'd for such desperate designs, Bigotted with a Belief of Merit, and present hopes of Heaven, are not such Milk-sops as the too often bastinado'd <hi>Settle,</hi> to fear Apprehending or being presently mangl'd to peices. Nor is there such an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possibilty but that a Villain so daring might have made an escape. For we read that the Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi> was Stabb'd by a bold and resolute <hi>Ruffian,</hi> in his Chamber, talking with Monsieur <hi>Sobieze,</hi> in the middle of his Army; and yet the Historian says, he got a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way undiscovered: Yet when they saw the Duke weltering in his Blood, every person look'd upon one another, marvelling who should do that horrid Act, till <hi>Felton</hi> stept out and discover'd himself. And thus one of your <hi>Plot-slayers</hi> main Impossibilitys falls to the ground. And I have dwelt the longer upon this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasing Story, to shew how little Credit there is to be giv'n to what follows, when he has acted so weakly and faintly, where his
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:201978:8"/>dead-doing hand against the <hi>Popish</hi> Plot, should have struck most keenly home. Suppositions and Objections are frivolous, fallaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and villanous; but let him Answer this, wheher it were not more probable that the <hi>Papists,</hi> a people generally of debauch'd and murderous Principles, that bear no consciences towards Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, persecuted by Penal Laws, should be induc'd out of their hatred of the Protestant Religion, and for the Advancement of their own, to remove the obstacles of their freedom and happiness by the Destruction of a Heretick Prince, then that a few inconsider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able persons without any support or encouragement, should dare to Create such a horrid and bloody Plot of ther own heads, and then venture their lives by daring to justifie it to the face of King and Parliament: And therefore this same crawling insect of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Poet, might have employ'd his time much better then in disgorging his insolent <hi>Gibes</hi> upon the Divine prevention of such Infernal Mischiefs.</p>
            <p>As little Reason he has to make <hi>Chimerical</hi> Armies, the sport of his loose Wit: For let him sneer at <hi>Armies of Satyrs</hi> and <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taurs marching through Cheapside,</hi> the bubbles of his Tragical <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricranium,</hi> yet the intent of raising Armies, &amp; the Promises and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations of Forreign Aid, the <hi>Nerum necessarium,</hi> were not only Sworn by the Evidence, which he derides, but evidently demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strable out of <hi>Coleman</hi>'s Letters. What else means this signal pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage? <hi>We have a mighty Work upon our hands, the Subduing of a Pestilent Heresie, which has domineer'd over great part of the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern World, a great while. There never was greater Hopes of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess since the Death of Queen</hi> Mary, <hi>till these our days. But the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position we are like to meet with, is also like to be great, so that it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports us to get all the Aid and Assistance we can.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And all this the <hi>Narrative-monger</hi> did once so really believe, that he upbraids and taxes those he once called <hi>Tories,</hi> for being so nice and scrupulous for mistrusting a <hi>Popish</hi> Plot, <hi>for want of sufficient Circumstances, when they could believe a Protestant Plot, without either Witnesses or Circumstances at all. And for disputing about raising of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and not one Commission found, and yet could swallow the raising of a Protestant Army, without either Commission or Commission Officer. Nay, the very When, Where or How, were no part of their Considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> But now, by what ill fate heav'n knows, but only for a little Pocket money, the same Scruples, the same Niceties, are crept into Mr. <hi>Settles</hi> Conscience; finding it no doubt as empty as his Pocket. And therefore, mounting upon the <hi>Rosinante</hi> of his own Vain Wit, he undertakes, like another <hi>Don Quixote,</hi> to Fight <hi>French</hi> Armies, <hi>Spanish</hi> Armies, and Armies of <hi>Jago</hi> Pilgrims, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out so much as the help of one <hi>Sancha Pancha.</hi> He would make ye believe, that the <hi>French</hi> King was half a Protestant, as having ravish'd from the <hi>Pope,</hi> the best flowers in his Garden, and bidding Defiance to the Thunder of his Excommunications: And thence insinuates that the <hi>French</hi> King car'd not what became of the Plot
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:201978:9"/>or the <hi>Popish</hi> Religion in <hi>England.</hi> Not considering, that the most bigotted Prince in <hi>Europe, Charles</hi> the V. at the same time that he was designing the destruction of the <hi>German</hi> Protestants, Besieg'd and took even <hi>Rome</hi> it self, and held the <hi>Pope</hi> Prisoner in his own City; and never minding that the <hi>French</hi> King was then, as now, aspiring to the Univerfal Monarchy, and might be therefore glad of an Opportunity to get footing in <hi>England,</hi> not out of any Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Design, but to make it the Acquist of his Ambition.</p>
            <p>As for the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> he tells us, his condition was such, that he had occasion for ten times more Armies then he had. As if a broken Merchant might not put out a sum of money, for his own advantage, at the same time that an Execution was Seizing upon his Warehouse.</p>
            <p>He is mighty merry at the thoughts of the <hi>Blind,</hi> which the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suites</hi> found out, of <hi>throwing the Death of the King, upon the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians.</hi> Tho it be well known to all the World, that it has been since, their cheif design to throw the whole Plot upon their backs. And it is to be fear'd, that some unwary people, who call themselves of the Episcopal Party (for I leave out the <hi>Papists,</hi> who want no information) do half believe it already. So far was it from being such an impudent peice of Madness or Lunacy as this <hi>Ninny-ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> of a Narrative-Monger, would make it; the worst at <hi>Absur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, Impossibilities</hi> and drawing of Consequences, that ever read <hi>For the due joyning.</hi> For were not his <hi>Genius</hi> wholly at the Devotion of his Pocket or his Codpeice, he might all along have observ'd, how the Papists themselves are puzl'd to disown a plot, but onely they would faine remove the Load of the Reproach from their own Shoulders.</p>
            <p>But then to talk of a <hi>Massacre,</hi> is the greatest sport to him in nature. For quo he, what need so many Commissions for the prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Popish Bishops, Abbots and Priors, when the People were all destroyed? Hold a little— Men do not alwaies perform what they speak in their Passion. They that tereaten'd not to leave a man that <hi>Piss'd against the wall.</hi> did not always put the utmost of the Menace in Execution. And the wiser sort, when they are once sure of the day, think it better to triumph over the Living then the Dead. On the other side the <hi>Papists</hi> have not been so compassi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate to the <hi>Hereticks,</hi> that a Massacre of the most Barbarous Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, may not be lay'd to their Charge. Witness that of the <hi>Albi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genses,</hi> where they destroy'd Men, Women and Children, with an exorabe Cruely, even to the depopulating of a large Territory. Nor may we omit the Irish Rebellion, a meer Inundation of Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Massacre. that spar'd neither Sex nor Age nor Parent, nor Friend, nor Relation, till it was stopp'd by force; and therefore, notwithstanding Mr. <hi>Shallowpates</hi> mirth, it would have been but ill trusting the <hi>Papists</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> had the Plot gon on. Now whether they would have cut our Throats with Brown Bills or blew Bills, thats not the Question. All this while, here's nothing to the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:201978:9"/>business, here's nothing said to the <hi>verum necessarium:</hi> for still the substantial part of the King's Evidence agrees with <hi>Coleman</hi>'s Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, that there were endeavors, and large endeavors too us'd among the <hi>Papists</hi> in <hi>England</hi> to subdue the <hi>pestilent Heresie</hi> of <hi>Protestan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tism,</hi> and to procure all the Aid and Assistance they could get. And therefore the extravagant Discourse of men flattering themselves with conceited hopes, which many times elevate the Fancy, even to a kind os Luxuriancie, is no Argument to invalidate the more subtle and solid Part and Conduct of the Plot. No, no, the Plot was too deeply laid to be undermin'd by such a young Sophister as <hi>Settle,</hi> or to be torn from the Cheeks of Truth by the Off-spring of a <hi>Tooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He takes great Advantage from the different accompts which <hi>Oates</hi> and <hi>Dugdale</hi> give of the various Discourses they heard of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of the Design. We understand him,—he would have had all the several Gangs and Clubbs of Plotters have all just jumpt in one and the same sence and opinion, like the Translators of the <hi>Septuagint.</hi> As if he could be such a <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> so blockishly ignorant of the world, not to know that where several people are engag'd, there will be se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Sir <hi>Politick Woodbe's,</hi> that will be putting their Oar i'th Boat where they are concern'd; one will be proposing this, another that, and many a Fool's Bolt will be shot, and this Discourse, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver so simple is Treason, and fit to be known by way of Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance. But from hence to bring a Conclusion there was no Plot! where was this Son of a Barber born?</p>
            <p>But now, quoth our <hi>Impertinent Plot-Thrasher,</hi> what think ye, if I <hi>prove the work was to have been done by no Armies at all?</hi> Why truly had he had any thing else in the world to do, he might have spar'd himself the labour; for so long as it was to be done, the cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er they did it, the less it would have cost 'em. However <hi>Ireland,</hi> one of the Executed Jesuites, was of opinion, that there was no way to bring the business about but by a considerable force, which he muster'd up to Fifty thousand, affirming a less number would not suffice. Neither did <hi>Langhorn</hi> absolutely deny at his Trial the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of Commissions, only he deny'd them to be seen upon his Desk. But I will not dispute the Case farther with <hi>E. Settle;</hi> for perhaps he might know more of the Plot then they that were hang'd did. And therefore for <hi>Jago-Pilgrims</hi> and <hi>Flandrian</hi> or <hi>French Armies,</hi> if he will not have 'em to carry on the Plot, let him take 'em to Garrison his own Castles in the Air. As for the <hi>Irish</hi> Plot, he swears by all the Idols of the <hi>Moabites,</hi> there could be no such thing: for if there were, then the King of <hi>Spain</hi> was a <hi>Blockhead,</hi> and the King of <hi>France</hi> a <hi>Lunatick,</hi> and ought to come to <hi>E. Settle</hi> to be better instructed in State-Politicks; for which, when they have learn'd effectually, they shall only make him a Leg, and thank him in two Verses broken of <hi>Horace,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>—Dii te, <hi>Damasippe,</hi> Deae{que}</l>
                  <l>Verum ob Consilium donent Tonsore.—</l>
               </q>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:201978:10"/>Now because most of his Romantick Objections against the <hi>Irish</hi> Plot depend upon <hi>Plunkett</hi>'s Trial, upon which he was condemn'd, I shall not trouble my self to make any further Defence for <hi>Courts</hi> of <hi>Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cature,</hi> then what has been made already.</p>
            <p>He is very inquisitive after the Reason why <hi>Pickering</hi> was to have had 1500<hi>l.</hi> and the four Ruffians but 20<hi>l.</hi> apiece? What's this to the destruction of the Plot? Every man makes as good a Bargain for himself as he can; and it is the property of a Ruffian to demand less for killing a man, then for lam-basting him. If they were Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of <hi>Rank</hi> and <hi>Quality,</hi> as he says they were, which was more then the Evidence themselves either knew or said, 'twas a sign they undertook what they did out of pure zeal and not for Money, as the <hi>Recanter</hi> wrote his Narrative. But these are Questions fitter for the Discussion of a Country Barbers Shop, then to trouble the thoughts of Rational men. For what tho <hi>Bedloe</hi> were the son of a Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler? What absurditie thence arises, but that he might be proffer'd his share of five thousand pound to head a band of <hi>Bravo's</hi> to execute a Murder? The <hi>Jesuites</hi> knew murder was dearer in <hi>England</hi> then in <hi>Italy.</hi> However since the Son of a Cobler Swore it, why should the Son of a Barber Question it? 'Twas pity the Jesuites had not known Mr. <hi>Settle</hi> at that time, to have made him their Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surer, that he might more equally and uprightly have proportion'd to every one their shares according to their Rank and Quality. No doubt but he would have given them an Excellent accompt of their Money at the Plots end.</p>
            <p>Tis a strange'thing; nothing well please this <hi>Plot-Swashbuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler.</hi> 'Tis such a Mr. Find-fault, why whats the matter? Why now forsooth, Sir <hi>Ed. Godfrey</hi> was not murder'd to his mind. Now if he were not murder'd according to the Protestant Poets mind, as he would have had it done, if he had had a finger in the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der then it could be no Tragedy, for he is old Dog at a Tragedy; and if no Tragedy, then was Sir <hi>Ed. Godfrey</hi> never Murder'd.</p>
            <p>But as if Heaven had infatuated all that go about to defend that <hi>execrable Murder,</hi> he makes such false Passes, such fallacious Objections, and mistaken Applications, that neither the <hi>Block<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head King of Spain,</hi> nor the <hi>Lunatick King of France,</hi> ever com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted grosser Errors in the height of their Stupidity.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Barbers Son</hi> does not observe that what the <hi>Coblers Son</hi> declar'd before the Lords, in reference to the fact it self, was only by relation from others. For that neither at the Tryal, nor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lords, did <hi>Bedloe</hi> undertake to distinguish the Parties that did the fact.</p>
            <p>In the next place, the <hi>Barbers Son</hi> does not observe, that there were Parties engag'd in his Murther; the Cobler's Son's Party, and <hi>Prance</hi>'s Party. Now it happen'd that <hi>Prance</hi>'s Party got the start of <hi>Bedloe</hi>'s. But when the fact was committed, both Parties clos'd, and fed their Curiosities with the beautiful Object of a Murder'd Heretick. Which is the true sence of <hi>Bedloe</hi>'s Deposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:201978:10"/>tho this Recanting <hi>Plot-Killer</hi> would so fain scrue it to his own wicked purpose.</p>
            <p>Thus it is plain that <hi>Bedloe</hi>'s Oath was either previous to the Fact, in relation to his Contract with <hi>La Phaire,</hi> or <hi>post factum,</hi> in reference to his being carry'd to view the dead Body.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prance</hi> Swore to the positive matter of fact, as it was acted by him and his accomplices, and so to all the succeeding circumstances of Removal and concealment of the massacr'd Body, till the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der was lay'd a sweetning, near Primrose Hill.</p>
            <p>To this Monsieur <hi>Flim-flam</hi> makes his first exception, that the Murder was commited without <hi>one syllable to any Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stions ask'd, or the least dispute about sending for Depositions,</hi> &amp;c. that is, he would have had them have made a <hi>Prologuee</hi> to their Tragedy, as he was us'd to do; but their Circumstances would admit of no such delays.</p>
            <p>Then he admires, that such a Fact should be committed in the <hi>sight of a Centinel, who had ten times more Authority and Power to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the Quarrel, then the Justice of the Peace had;</hi> forgetting that it was positively sworn that there was no Centinel there.</p>
            <p>In the next place he is angry, that the Murderers did not lay the Body in the Street, and come out like <hi>Felton,</hi> and bravely confess the Fact, but that they remov'd him from place to place, as their Fears and Jealousies prompted them, and the heinousness of the Crime required; which he looks upon as a great Absurdity.</p>
            <p>And now, what may we think of such a <hi>Bungler</hi> as this, who having undertaken to vindicate Murder and Treason in the highest degree, and the Innocence of the <hi>Papists,</hi> under such a bloody Charge of <hi>Impious Plot,</hi> and <hi>Infernal Conspiracy,</hi> with a glorious presumption to have outdone all others that went before him, could find no better Implements to advance his Reputation of being the Wonder of his Age for compleating such an <hi>Herculean</hi> Labour, but a company of moth eaten, baffl'd, silly, <hi>nitty Objections,</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Absurdities, which his old <hi>Sculler-Pot-companions</hi> would have been asham'd of? We may justly believe that for half the Sum proffer'd to the <hi>Cobler's Son,</hi> the <hi>Barber's Son,</hi> had he had as much courage to assault a man, as to lift up his hand against a surpriz'd Woman, would not have stuck to have committed the same inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Murder himself?</p>
            <p>Yet after all these Paltry Reflections upon the cruelty and strange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of the <hi>Assassination,</hi> he has the insolence to affirm, that after <hi>Hill, Berry</hi> and <hi>Green</hi> were apprehended, all <hi>Difficulties were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:201978:11"/>and <hi>all Differences adjusted:</hi> As if the Judges of the Land sate in their High Courts of Judicature to reconcile the Incongrui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Incoherences of perjur'd Evidence; a Crime certainly not to be forgiv'n by injur'd <hi>Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having made this frivolous Attack upon Sir <hi>Ed. B. Godfrey</hi>'s mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, he falls into another Extasie, and admires that of all those Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Pacquets of Treasonable correspondence sent by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Post, none should be <hi>intercepted,</hi> none preserv'd by the Disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verers, for the justification and proof of the Discovery.</p>
            <p>Where's the Improbability? For the King has no Inquisitor that sits in his publick Office to break up Gentlemens Letters; it is that which the great obstruction of Commerce will not allow. And yet there was a certain Pacquet sent by the common Post, directed to Father <hi>Beningfield,</hi> which by an unlucky Fate, mist falling into the hands of those who would have made better use of it. No man can be so indiscreet as to believe that the <hi>Irish</hi> Rebellion was carri'd on without correspondence, and yet it brake out like a Torrent with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out discovery.</p>
            <p>And then for the latter Part of the Objection, the <hi>Protestant Poet</hi> has made a most clever Answer to it himself. For when the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal put this Question to Pope <hi>Joan</hi>'s Witnesses, <hi>Can you produce those Letters?</hi> that is to say, such Letters as were to prove the D. of <hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ony</hi>'s Heresie. The <hi>Protestant Poet</hi> makes Answer,
<q>
                  <l>No, my Lord—</l>
                  <l>For still the cautious <hi>Damasus</hi> made his Soul</l>
                  <l>His Treasons Cabinet; all dangerous Papers</l>
                  <l>No sooner read, but burnt.—</l>
               </q> So ingenious he could be for Pope <hi>Joan</hi> at a pinch; but in his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries and a discarded Protestant Cause, the greatest <hi>Bufflehead</hi> in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Post-script</hi> is like the Fools Part in a <hi>Fortune-Playhouse-Comedy,</hi> to make the sixpenny Gallery Sport; you there finding him a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <hi>Jack Pudding,</hi> and like another <hi>Merry Andrew,</hi> telling the Jesu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites, what He, the <hi>Worshipful Protestant Poet</hi> would have done, had he been of their <hi>Consult.</hi> And under the Cover of a Fancy of his own, mistak'nly carried on, beyond Sence or Reason, drolling with the King, and taxing the Duke of <hi>Ormond</hi> of ill management; so that in the next Popish Plot, he has bespoke himself to be a both sides. On the one side, chief Manager of the Plot, on the other side, President of the Councel, and Lord Lieutenant of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:201978:11"/>
            <p> But it is high time to have done with such an impertinent <hi>Son of Necessity,</hi> the general scorn of his Recantation, and disdain of his Nefarious Attempt being sufficient to condemn him. And indeed it might be expected, that ere this he should have condemn'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self. And that we might have had Tidings of his drown'd Carkass being taken up at <hi>White Friers</hi> Stairs, by some of his old Friends the Watermen's Boys. The lightest punishment to which he could have sentenc'd himself for having thus at the instigation of his Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, so boldly presum'd to vent an Infamous and Rebellious <hi>Libel,</hi> with all the Reflexions that hungry Falshood and Poetick Forgery could invent, upon all the <hi>Judicial Proceedings</hi> of the Nation. A new Surprize upon the Kingdom, which cannot well be determined whether greatest, at the Irreligion of a converted <hi>Infidel,</hi> defending Acts of Impiety, or at the Confidence of a Subject contending a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Justice of his Sovereign.</p>
            <p>For to give him <hi>Dilemma</hi> for his <hi>Dilemma;</hi> Either he is in the right, and the Embody'd <hi>Prudence</hi> and <hi>Justice</hi> of the Nation were in the wrong; or the Embody'd <hi>Justice</hi> and <hi>Prudence</hi> of the Nation were in the Right, and he is in the wrong. And then what sort of open Retaliation he deserves for the worst of Crimes, they whose Wisdom, whose Justice, whose Integrity, in the highest places of Dignity he has so insolently and scandalously reproach'd and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronted, are best able to determin. Nor is there any thing that can pretend to save him, but this one single Expedient, that while all Men know him to be a meer Natural Animal of a <hi>Poet,</hi> his whole Recantation and Narrative must be taken for a <hi>Fiction.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>